You have one life, don't settle for mediocrity.
Don't settle for mediocrity.
And I think the only, like people debate intelligence, for example, right?
We talk about IQ tests and all that.
But I think the only true test of intelligence is if you get what you
want out of life.
And there are two parts to that.
One is getting what you want, so you know how to get it.
And the second is wanting the right things, knowing what to want in the first
place.
I could want to be a six foot eight basketball player and I'm not going
to get that.
So it's wanting the wrong thing.
That's wanting something that you can't get.
That's wanting something you can't get.
It's also wanting something that you don't want.
Yeah, wanting something that's a booby prize.
There are plenty of booby prizes out there too, right?
I haven't heard that word in about 20 years.
Yeah, prizes that are just not worth having or that create their own problems.
But if you're not careful, you can end up in a place in life not
only that you don't want to be, but one that you didn't even mean to
get to.
That's if you're kind of proceeding unconsciously.
But how many people are?
And usually I think people end up there because they are going on autopilot with
sort of societal expectations or other people's expectations.
So, you know, or out of guilt or out of like mimetic desire.
You know, Peter Thiel has this whole thing from Rene Girard about how mimetic desires
or desires are picked up from other people.
And some of those are automatically baked into society, like, you know, go to law
school, go to med school, go to whatever, go to business school.
Or they might be from watching what your friends are doing and, you know, the
other monkeys are doing.
Or it might just be what your parents' expectations are.
It might be a guilt.
Guilt is just society's voice speaking in your head, socially programmed so you'll be a
good little monkey and do things that are good for the tribe.
But I think the best outcomes come when you think it through for yourself and
decide for yourself.
And I don't think people spend enough time deciding.
For example, we run on these four-year cycles.
In Silicon Valley, you go join a startup, you invest your stock over four years.
That's the standard.
Okay.
In college, you know, you go for four years.
High school, you go for four years.
Some things take longer.
You know, you have children, they hit puberty nine years later.
That's like a nine-year cycle until that relationship changes.
But we're used to these fairly long cycles, multi-year cycles in which we are committed
to things.
You go to law school, you know, four or five-year cycle.
You go be a lawyer, 40-year cycle.
These are very long cycles.
the amount of time we spend deciding what to do and who to do it
with very short very very short right we spend you know three months deciding one
month deciding on a job where we're going to be for 10 years or five
years and because a lot of discovery is path dependent where the next thing you
find on the path is dependent on where you were on the previous path you
sort of start going down this vector that is a very long distance people decide
frivolously which city to live in and that's going to decide who their friends are,
what their jobs are, their opportunity, their weather, their food supply, their air supply, quality
of life.
It's such an important decision, but people spend so little time thinking it through.
I would argue that if you're making a four-year decision, spend a year thinking it
through, like really thinking it through.
25% of the time.
Yeah, exactly.
There's the secretary theorem.
I don't know if you know that one.
After you've done this many people, pick the best one of the next however many.
That's right.
Yeah, the secretary theorem is this computer science professor is trying to figure out how
much time he should spend interviewing secretaries and then how long to keep the secretary.
So let's say he's going to have a secretary for 10 years.
Does he keep searching for, you know, one year, two years, three years, one month,
two months?
What is the optimal time?
And it turns out that the optimal time is somewhere around a third, about a
third of the way through, you take the best person you've worked with and try
to find someone that good or better.
So by the time you've gone about a third of the way through, you have
excuse me seen enough that you now have a sense of what the bar is
and then anybody who meets or exceeds that bar is good enough and this applies
to dating this applies to jobs and careers this applies generally but the interesting thing
about the secretary theorem is that it's actually not time-based it's not based on one
third of the time it's iteration based the number of candidates the number of shots
you took on goal that's right so you want to have lots and lots of
iterations So in that sense, you need to bail out quickly and you need to
be decisive quickly.
That's right.
You need to take opportunities quickly and bail out quickly.
Correct.
Like if you go back and you look through failed relationships, probably the biggest regret
will be staying in the relationship after you knew it was over.
Exactly.
You should have left sooner.
The moment you knew it wasn't going to work out, you should have moved on.
So in that sense, I think Malcolm Gladwell popularized this idea of 10,000 hours to
mastery.
I would say it's actually 10,000 iterations to mastery.
It's not actually 10,000.
It's some unknown number.
but it's about the number of iterations that drive the learning curve.
And iteration is not repetition.
Repetition is a different thing.
Repeating is doing the same thing over and over.
Iteration is modifying it with a learning and then doing another version of it.
So that's error correction.
So if you get 10,000 error corrections in anything, you will be an expert at
it.
Don't partner with cynics and pessimists.
You mentioned there about the people who've got a nightmare going on at home and
are trying to fix the world.
but a lot of the time that cynicism and pessimism we find in ourselves.
We see the world, whether we want to, whether it's because we've imbibed what the
news or the negative people around us have said, or it's a bit more kind
of endogenous than that.
It's just sort of in us.
It's the way that we see the world.
How can people avoid cynicism and pessimism within themselves?
Yeah, cynicism and pessimism is a tough one.
We're naturally hardwired for it.
Again, and I go back to evolution, I'm sorry to keep harping on evolution, but
within biology, there's very few good explanatory theories know, theory of evolution by natural selection
is probably the best one.
So if you can't explain something about life or psychology or human nature through evolution,
then you probably don't have a good theory for it.
And I would say that pessimism is another one that comes out of this, which
is in the natural environment, you're hardwired to be pessimistic.
Because let's say that I see something rustling in the woods.
And if I move towards it, and it turns out to be food and prey,
then good, I get to eat one meal.
But if it turns out to be a predator, I get eaten.
And that's the end of that.
So we are hardwired to avoid ruin and just dying.
So we are naturally hardwired to be pessimists.
But modern society is very different.
Despite whatever problems you may have with modern society, it is far, far safer than
living in the jungle and just trying to survive.
And the opportunities and the upside are nonlinear.
For example, when you're investing, if you short a stock, the most money you can
make is 2x.
You just lose, you know, if the stock goes to zero, you double your money.
But if the stock is an X NVIDIA and it goes 100x or 1,000x, you
make a lot of money.
So upside, because of leverage, is nearly unlimited.
Also in modern society, because there's so many different people you can interact with, if
you go on a date and it fails, there are infinite more people to go
on a date with.
In a tribal system, there might have been 20 people and you can't even get
through all of them.
so modern society is far more forgiving of failure and you just have to sort
of neocordically realize and override that you have to realize that you're much more running
a search function to find the thing that'll work and then that one thing will
pay off in massive compounding once you find your mate for the rest of your
life you find your wife or your husband then you can compound in that relationship
it's okay if you had 50 failed dates in between the same way once you
find the one business you're meant to plow into and it'll compound returns it's okay
if you had 50 small fail ventures or 50 small fail job interviews.
The number of failures doesn't matter.
And so there's no point in being a pessimist.
You want to be an optimist, but I would say you want to be skeptical
about specific things.
Every specific opportunity is probably a fail, but you want to be optimistic in the
general.
In the general, you want to be like, something in here is going to work.
How do you navigate that tension?
I mean, exactly as I said, I'm optimistic in the general that if something fails
right now, then this is a little woo-woo, but it wasn't meant to be.
It was a learning experience.
It was an iteration.
As long as I learned something from it, then it's a win.
If I didn't learn from it, then it's a loss.
But as long as you're learning and you keep iterating fast and cutting your losses
quickly, then when you find the right thing, you have to be optimistic and compound
into it.
So you don't want to jump into the first thing.
You don't want to marry the first person you date necessarily, unless you got very
lucky.
But you want to investigate and explore very, very quickly until you find the match.
And then you have to be willing to go all in you have to be
willing to move your chips at the center of the table so both those uh
both those uh approaches are required so it's a barbell strategy it's sort of black
or it's white and most people are sort of stuck in this gray bit and
like half in but i'm kind of don't really know if i am and i
also think like labels like pessimists optimists cynic introvert extrovert these are very
self-limiting.
Humans are very dynamic.
There are times when you feel like being introverted.
There are times when you feel like being extroverted.
There are contexts in which you'll be pessimistic.
There are contexts in which you'll be optimistic.
Leave all those labels alone.
It's better just to look at the problem at hand.
Look at reality the way it is.
Try to take yourself out of the equation in a sense.
Obviously, you're involved, but motivated reasoning is the worst kind of reasoning.
You're not going to find truth through highly motivated reasoning.
You have to be objective.
And objective means trying to take yourself out of it as much as possible, or
at least your personality out of it as much as possible.
And so to the extent you run with this thick identity and personality, it's going
to cloud your judgment.
It's going to try and lock you into the past.
If you say, I'm a depressed, unhappy person, yeah, I'm going to be unhappy.
That's a way of locking yourself into your past.
Even saying, I have trauma, I have PTSD.
Yeah, you feel something.
There are memories, there are flashes, there are occasional bad feelings, but don't define yourself
by it, because then you'll lock it into your identity and just going to loop
on it.
It's better to stay flexible because reality is always changing and you have to be
able to adapt to it.
Adaptation is also intelligence.
Adaptation is survival.
Adaptation is kind of how you're here.
You're here because you're an adapter and your ancestors were adapters.
So to adapt, you'll be able to see things clearly.
And if you're seeing them through your own identity, it's going to cloud your judgment.
In other news, this episode is brought to you by Function.
Staying on top of your health requires more than just an annual physical, which is
why I partnered with Function.
They run lab tests twice a year to track over 100 biomarkers and monitor for
early signs of thousands of diseases.
They even screen for 50 types of cancer at stage one, which is five times
more data than you get from an annual physical.
You receive insights from a team of expert physicians who provide a detailed written clinician
summary for their observations and then phone consultations for any critical findings.
Getting these lab tests done would usually cost thousands, but with Function, it is only $499.
And right now, you can get the exact same blood panels that I get and
bypass their wait list by going to the link in the description below or heading
to functionhealth.com slash modern wisdom.
That's functionhealth.com slash modern wisdom.
Thank you very much for tuning in.
If you enjoyed that clip with Naval, just a mere taster, the full length episode
is available right here.
Go on.
Watch it.